<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>/var/ - networking</title><link href="https://spapas.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://spapas.github.io/feeds/networking.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://spapas.github.io/</id><updated>2021-09-21T14:20:00+03:00</updated><subtitle>Various programming stuff</subtitle><entry><title>A forward and reverse proxy primer for the layman</title><link href="https://spapas.github.io/2021/09/21/layman-proxy-primer/" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-09-21T14:20:00+03:00</published><updated>2021-09-21T14:20:00+03:00</updated><author><name>Serafeim Papastefanos</name></author><id>tag:spapas.github.io,2021-09-21:/2021/09/21/layman-proxy-primer/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;A primer for explaining forward and reverse proxies to the&amp;nbsp;layman&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Before some days I&amp;#8217;d &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=28381220"&gt;written an answer on &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HN&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; where I explained as simply as possible
how a forward and a reverse proxy is working and what is the difference between them. In this article
I&amp;#8217;m going to extend this answer a bit to make it a full post and clarify some things even&amp;nbsp;more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Forward and reverse proxies is an important concept that a lot of technical people aren&amp;#8217;t familiar with.
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTTP&lt;/span&gt; Proxying is a process of forwarding (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTTP&lt;/span&gt;) requests from one server to the other. So when an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTTP&lt;/span&gt;
client issues a request to the server, the request will pass through the proxy server and be forwarded to the
destination server (called the origin server). This explanation is true both for forward and reverse&amp;nbsp;proxying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="forward-proxy"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Forward&amp;nbsp;Proxy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A forward proxy is used when an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTTP&lt;/span&gt; Client (i.e a browser) wants to access resources in the internet
but isn&amp;#8217;t allowed to connect directly to the public internet so instead uses the&amp;nbsp;proxy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Usually companies don&amp;#8217;t allow unrestricted access to the internet from their internal network.
Thus the internal users would need to use a proxy to access the internet. This is the concept of the forward proxy.
What happens is that when an internal user want to access an internet resource (i.e www.google.com) her client (i.e browser)
will ask a specific server (the proxy server) for that resource. The client needs to be configured properly with the address
of the proxy&amp;nbsp;server.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So instead of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.google.com"&gt;http://www.google.com&lt;/a&gt; the browser will access &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://proxy.company.com/?url=www.google.com"&gt;http://proxy.company.com/?url=www.google.com&lt;/a&gt; and the
proxy will fetch the results and return them to you. If the browser wants to access &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.google.com"&gt;https://www.google.com&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt;
a configured proxy server it will get a network&amp;nbsp;error.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s an image that explains&amp;nbsp;this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Forward proxy" src="/images/fw_proxy.png" style="width: 800px;" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The internal client can access the internal web server directly without problems. However he cannot access
the internet server directly so he needs to use the proxy to access&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing that needs to be made crystal is that the fact that your browser works with the proxy does not mean
that any other &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTTP&lt;/span&gt; clients you use will also work. For example, you may want to run &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;curl&lt;/tt&gt; or &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;wget&lt;/tt&gt; to download
some files from an external server; these programs will not work without setting a proxy (usually by setting the http_proxy
and https_proxy environment variables or by passing a parameter). Also, the proxy only works for &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTTP&lt;/span&gt; requests. If you are
in a private network without external access you will &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; be able to access non-&lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTTP&lt;/span&gt; resources. For example you will not be able
to access your non-company mail server (which uses either &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IMAP&lt;/span&gt; or &lt;span class="caps"&gt;POP3&lt;/span&gt;) from behind your company&amp;#8217;s network. Typically, you&amp;#8217;ll use
a web client for accessing your&amp;nbsp;mails.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it seems that using a proxy heavily restricts the internal users usage of internet. What are the advantages of using a forward&amp;nbsp;proxy?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Security: Since the internal computers of a company will not have internet access there&amp;#8217;s no easy way for attackers to access these&amp;nbsp;computers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Content moderation: The company through the proxy can block access to various internet sites (i.e social network, gaming etc) that the users shouldn&amp;#8217;t access during&amp;nbsp;work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Caching: The proxy server can have a cache so when multiple users access the same internet resource it will downloaded only once saving the company&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;bandwidth.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Especially the security thing is so important that almost all corporate (or university etc) networks will use a proxy server and never
allow direct access to the&amp;nbsp;internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A well known, open source forward proxy server is &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.squid-cache.org/"&gt;Squid&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="reverse-proxy"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reverse&amp;nbsp;proxy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A reverse proxy is an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTTP&lt;/span&gt; server that &amp;#8220;proxies&amp;#8221; (i.e forwards) some (or all) requests it receives to a different &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTTP&lt;/span&gt;
server and returns the answer back. For example, a company may have a couple of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTTP&lt;/span&gt; servers in its internal network. These
servers have private addresses and cannot be accessed through the internet. To allow external users to access these servers,
the company will configure a reverse proxy server that will forward the requests to the internal servers as seen in the&amp;nbsp;picture:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Reverse proxy" src="/images/reverseproxy.png" style="width: 800px;" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What happens is that the proxy server will forward requests that fulfill some specific
criteria to other web servers. The criteria may be requests that have
* a specific host (forward the requests that have a hostname of &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;www.server1.company.com&lt;/tt&gt; to the internal server named &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;server1&lt;/tt&gt; and &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;www.server2.company.com&lt;/tt&gt; to the internal server named &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;server2&lt;/tt&gt;)
* or a specific port (forward requests in the port 81 to &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;server1&lt;/tt&gt; and requests in the port 82 to &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;server2&lt;/tt&gt;)
* or even a particular path (forward requests with the path &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;www.company.com/server1&lt;/tt&gt; to &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;server1&lt;/tt&gt; and requests with the path &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;www.company.com/server2&lt;/tt&gt; to &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;server2&lt;/tt&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;or even other criteria that may be&amp;nbsp;decided.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#8217;s see some example of reverse&amp;nbsp;proxying:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A characteristic example of reverse proxy is the well-known 3-tier architecture  (web server / app server / database server). The web server is used to serve all requests but it &amp;#8220;proxies&amp;#8221;  (forwards) some of the requests to the app server. This is used because the web server cannot serve dynamic  replies but can serve static replies like for example&amp;nbsp;files.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Offloading the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SSL&lt;/span&gt; (https) security to a particular web server. This server will store the private key of your certificate and terminate the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SSL&lt;/span&gt; connections. It will then forward the requests to the internal web servers using plain &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTTP&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTTP&lt;/span&gt; load balancer will proxy the requests to a set of other servers based on some algorithm to share the load (i.e the HAProxy software load balancer or even a hardware load&amp;nbsp;balancer)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A reverse proxy can be used to act as a security and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DOS&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#8220;shield&amp;#8221; for your web servers. It will check the requests for common attack patterns and forward them to your servers only if they are&amp;nbsp;safe&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A reverse proxy can be used for caching; it will return cached versions of resources if they are available to avoid overloading the application&amp;nbsp;servers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CDN&lt;/span&gt; (content delivery network) is more or less a set of glorified reverse proxy servers that act as a first step for serving the user&amp;#8217;s requests (based on the geographic location) also offering security protection and caching (this is what akamai or cloudflare&amp;nbsp;do)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As can be seen from the previous examples there are a lot of apps that do reverse proxying, for example apache &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HTTP&lt;/span&gt;, nginx, HAProxy, varnish cache et&amp;nbsp;al.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notice that while there&amp;#8217;s only one forward proxy, there could be a (large) chain of reverse proxies when accessing a remote server.
Let&amp;#8217;s take a look at a rather complex scenario: A user in a corporate network will access an application in another network. In this case the user&amp;#8217;s request
may pass&amp;nbsp;through:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;forward proxy (squid) -&amp;gt;
security server / &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CDN&lt;/span&gt; (akamai) -&amp;gt;
ssl termination (nginx) -&amp;gt;
caching (varnish) -&amp;gt;
web server (nginx again) -&amp;gt;
app server (tomcat or gunicorn or &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IIS&lt;/span&gt; etc)
as can be seen on the following&amp;nbsp;image:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Reverse proxy" src="/images/reverseproxy2.png" style="width: 800px;" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notice that is this case (which is not uncommon) there are six (05) servers between your client and the application&amp;nbsp;server!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One common problem with this is that unless &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; the intermediate servers are configured properly
(by properly modifying and passing the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/HTTP/Headers/X-Forwarded-For"&gt;X-Forwarded-For&lt;/a&gt; header)
you won&amp;#8217;t be able to retrieve the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IP&lt;/span&gt; of the user that did the initial&amp;nbsp;request.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="networking"></category><category term="forward-proxy"></category><category term="reverse-proxy"></category><category term="proxy"></category><category term="networking"></category><category term="http"></category></entry></feed>